Finding Aid for Human Rights Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.) Records, 1970-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Human Rights Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records 1970-1979, 1971-1975
Human Rights Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
1 oversize folders
3 linear feet
0586 Bt 2; Bt Outsize
The Human Rights Party (HRP) of Ann Arbor was a radical socialist third party that influenced local politics in the period 1971 to 1975. The record group contains organizational and campaign documents of several parties including predecessor and successor parties to HRP. Campaign materials, platforms, position statements and numerous newspaper clippings along with committee and meeting minutes form the bulk of the records of this activist organization.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received from Philip Carroll in June, 2005. (Donor no. 9602 )
The record group is open to research.
During the winter of 1970, a series of open conventions were held in Ann Arbor resulting in the formation of Radical Independent Party (RIP) by local activists. In April 1971, RIP ran a write-in campaign with Doug Cornell and Jerry DeGrieck, as candidates for Mayor and Second Ward Councilman. In June, RIP member, Bob Hefner, ran in the non-partisan School Board election, gathering 11% of the city-wide vote. Needing stronger recognition, RIP decided to affiliate with the Human Rights Party of Michigan, a statewide third party formed by dissident radical Democrats. Legislation had just been passed allowing eighteen-year olds to vote and permitting college students to vote where they attend school. The Human Rights Party of Ann Arbor was formed with the intent to influence local politics. HRP made all decisions at open meetings. Day-to-day functions were coordinated by a Steering Committee whose decisions were reviewed by the membership at open meetings.
HRP first appeared on a ballot in Ann Arbor in April, 1972, in a City Council election in which Jerry DeGrieck and Nancy Wechsler won two of the five contested seats Because of the Council make-up, neither Republicans nor Democrats could successfully function without HRP support. Through cooperation with Democratic council members, the HRP radical legislative agenda was passed including a $5 pot law, a ban on non-returnable bottles, a shift of $600,000 of revenue-sharing funds to child and health care, and a strong human rights ordinance against sexual discrimination. HRP supported local strikes: Buhr Tool, Commission on Professional Hospital Activities (CPHA), and Mackinac Jack's.
In the 1973 City Council election, the Republicans gained a 7-2-2 majority, enabling the Council to repeal most of the HRP program. Benita Kaimowitz was unsuccessful with her bid for mayor. Frank Shoichet and Andrei Joseph lost in the 2nd and 3rd wards respectively. The Rainbow People's Party left the HRP after a disagreement over David Sinclair's candidacy, further weakening it
In 1974, Kathy Kozachenko won the 2nd ward council seat, while Beth Brunton lost the 1st ward. All three HRP City Council officials were openly gay, another revolutionary issue at the time. The $5 marijuana fine was reinstated. The focal issue of rent control was defeated by the voters. HRP successfully placed preferential voting for Mayor on the November ballot. For the first time HRP of Michigan ran a full slate of candidates, with Zoltan Ferency leading the ticket with his bid for Governor.
By 1975, HRP in Ann Arbor was in the decline. HRP renamed itself as the Socialist Human Rights Party but met no success thereafter. In 1977 the remnants of HRP organizers identified with the People's Party and Socialist Party of Michigan.
The records of HRP consist mainly of campaign activities, campaign issues, platforms, and clippings. The record group is divided into six series: Radical Independent Party, 1970-1971, Human Rights Party Organization, 1972-1975, HRP Campaigns, Socialist Human Rights Party, 1975-1977, Human Rights Party of Michigan, 1971-1976, and the People's Party, 1972-1979. In this collection, focal political issues are filed under the Steering Committee, if not separately foldered. Clippings are a major source of information and researchers should consult them for details.
Subjects:
Human Rights Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Elections--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Radical Independent Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Radicalism--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Socialist Human Rights Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Human Rights Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor Tenants Union.; Demonstrations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Carroll, Phil.; Political elections--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Radical Independent Party 1970-1971
  The Radical Independent Party, 1970-1971 series includes documents, information on campaign activities, and clippings.
  - Background Information 1969 (Box 1)
  - Platform Convention 1971
    - History (Box 1)
    - City Democratic Platform, Mayor Harris 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Draft Documents (Box 1)
  - Campaigns 1971
    - Steering Committee (Box 1)
    - City Charter Amendment (Box 1)
    - City Council and Mayor, Doug Cornell, Jerry DeGrieck (Box 1)
    - School Board, Bob Hefner (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Support for Strikers (Box 1)
- Human Rights Party of Ann Arbor Organization 1972-1975
  Human Rights Party Organization, 1972-1975 series encompasses official documents, platforms, photos, fliers, and correspondence. Audio tapes of commercial spots are also included.
  - Merger with RIP 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - History (Box 1)
  - Constitution (Box 1)
  - Platform Convention 1972
    - Agendas and Minutes (Box 1)
    - Platform and Platform in Brief (Box 1)
  - Audio tapes, short commercial spots undated (Box 1)
    (also public hearing on police 2/15/1973)
  - Correspondence 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Fliers undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Candidates 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - Phil Carroll 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Tenants Union, Rent Control demonstrations (Box 1)
  - DVD - 1992 reunion "Big Chill II" (Box 1)
- HRP Campaigns
  HRP Campaigns series covers the local political activities in Ann Arbor, substantiated by clippings from the Ann Arbor News and The Michigan Daily. Many clippings were not dated or identified as to publication. In general the Michigan Daily offered more detailed coverage of HRP.
  - Campaign Posters (Box 1)
    (oversize folder Bt)
  - 1972
    - City Council: Jerry DeGrieck, Nancy Wechsler
      (includes Steering Committee minutes)
      - Election April 3, 1972 (Box 1)
      - Anti-war Ordinance April, 1972 (Box 1)
    - School Board: Curtis Holt, Gretchen Wilson, Sonia Yaco
      - Conference for Educational Change April 28, 1972 (Box 1)
      - Educational Issue, Phil Carroll (Box 1)
      - Minutes, Fliers (Box 1)
    - Steering Committee (Box 1)
    - County Convention August 1972
      - Constitution of Human Rights Party of Washtenaw County (Box 1)
      - November Election Results (Box 1)
      - Roster (Box 1)
    - City Council Issues
      - Miscellaneous position papers (Box 1)
      - Police Chief Walter Krasny (Box 1)
      - Revenue Sharing (Box 1)
      - Strikebreakers Ordinance (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1973
    - City Council and Mayor: Benita Kaimowitz, Andrei Joseph, Frank Shoichet, Phil Carroll, John Minock
      - City Report (Box 2)
      - Candidates (Box 2)
        (includes promotional materials)
      - Primary (Box 2)
      - Election (Box 2)
      - Steering Committee Minutes, Issues (Box 2)
    - School Board: Leonard Sklar, Sonia Yaco, Diana Autin (Box 2)
    - Fall Campaign Issues (Box 2)
    - HRP Positions (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1974
    - City Council and Mayor: Carol Ernst, Beth Brunton, Kathy Kozachenko, Harry Kervorkian, Phil Carroll, Jesse Hall
      - Candidates (Box 2)
      - Clippings (Box 2)
      - Election (Box 2)
      - Issues
        - Marijuana (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous issues (Box 2)
        - Preferential Voting (Box 2)
        - Rent Control (Box 2)
      - Steering Committee (Box 2)
    - School Board: Astrid Beck, Larry Mann
      - Candidates (Box 2)
      - Clippings (Box 2)
    - County Convention
      - Agenda, Issues (Box 2)
      - County Commission: Diane Hall, Marty Wegbreit: (Box 2)
    - Fall Campaign
      - Issues, Press releases (Box 2)
      - Phil Carroll for US Representative, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1975
    - Scrapbooks
      - December 1974-April 1975 (Box 2)
      - City Council Election 1975 (Box 2)
      - April 1975-November 1975 (Box 2)
        (includes some minutes)
    - Minutes January-March, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Clippings (Box 3)
    - Council Campaign, Spring 1975, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Socialist Human Rights Party 1975-1977
  Socialist Human Rights Party, 1975-1977 series includes: minutes, campaign information, city council issues and clippings covering the brief existence of this party.
  - City Council Issues, Kozachenko 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Campaigns
    - Council Campaign, Spring 1976 (Box 3)
    - Fall Campaign 1976 (Box 3)
    - Council Campaign, Spring 1977 (Box 3)
  - Clippings 1976-1977 (Box 3)
- Human Rights Party of Michigan 1971-1976
  Human Rights Party of Michigan, 1971-1976 series covers the beginning of this third party to the defection of Zoltan Ferency in 1976. Platforms, clippings, issues, and a four-year newsletter run are included.
  - Minutes 1971-1976 (Box 3)
  - State HRP Constitution and Platform August 1972 (Box 3)
  - Washtenaw County Human Rights Party 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Newsletter 1972-1976 (Box 3)
  - Campaigns
    - 1972 State Campaign (Box 3)
    - 1973
      - Kalamazoo (Box 3)
      - Ypsilanti (Box 3)
    - 1974 State Campaign
      - Candidates (Box 3)
      - Clippings (Box 3)
      - Platform (Box 3)
  - Issues 1976-1979
    - Defections 1976 (Box 3)
    - Independent Candidate for U.S. President 1976 (Box 3)
    - Minor Party Status 1976-1977 (Box 3)
    - Red Squad 1977 (Box 3)
- The People's Party 1972-1979
  The series, The People's Party, 1972-1979 includes information about HRP members, Kathy Kozachenko, Eric Jackson, Phil Carroll, and Nancy Wechsler, who were involved in the PP. Like the HRP, the PP faced demise in 1977 and considered merger with the Socialist Party. Phil Carroll, who ran for National Committee in 1977, has correspondence in this series.
  - Communications, Correspondence 1972-1975, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Fliers undated (Box 3)
  - Grass Roots, People's Party National Publication, June 1972-August/September 1975 (Box 3)
  - National Conventions
    - St. Louis July 27-30, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Denver June 30-July 4, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Indianapolis July 4-6, 1974 (Box 3)
    - St. Louis August 25-31, 1975 (Box 3)
    - San Francisco August 1976 (Box 3)
    - New York City November 25-27, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Publications, Correspondence 1977-1979 (Box 3)
Related Material
The John and Leni Sinclair collection contains HRP records, particularly dealing with the campaign of David Sinclair and Frank Shoichet in the Second Ward Primary in 1974. Other related collections include: the papers of Robert Alexander and of William McNitt, and the Contemporary History Project oral interviews.